Guide to the Pacific Slope Manuscripts, 1832-1953
Department of Special Collections
Pacific Slope Manuscripts,
1832-1953
Special Collections M0153
2.5 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Provenance:
Varied sources
Access Restrictions
None.
Scope and Contents Note:
This collection pertains to the history of the Pacific Slope from 1832 until 1953. Included are notes, manuscripts, and typescripts on the founding and development of the California Mission system; letters, legal documents, and manuscripts dealing with early land claims, businesses, and legal cases; letters on political issues in California in the 1890s; political cartoons; family letters (1850s); historical biographies; manuscripts on Oregon history by Samuel J. Parker (1893); business correspondence; and materials on the San Francisco Reform Movement (1909-1910), the Society of California Pioneers, the Committee of Vigilance, the San Francisco Fire Department, and the Savage Mining Company (1864-1891). Also included are newsclipping scrapbooks (1870-1872) and maps of Oregon territory (1838) and the Whitman Trail (1834-1847).
CONTAINER LIST
- Briggs, Ella (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - 1. Postcard from bank asking to examine bankbook, 1898 June 27.
- Cherington, Reed B. - California Missions (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. "Who's Who in California Mission History." Notebook.
  - 2. "The Present Condition of the Missions." Typescript and summary of a talk, 1925 Ocotober 20
  - 3. "Commandante Rivera." Typescript, 3 pp.
  - 4. "How the Pueblo Church Obtained Its Bell." Carbon and typescript.
  - 5. "The Founder of the California Missions, the Two-Hundredth Anniversary of His Birth." Typed draft and typescript.
  - 6. The story of Missions, etc. Notes, holograph.
  - 7. "Regulations for mission." Typescript.
  - 8. Misc. holograph notes.
- Cherington, Reed B. - California Missions (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. "Founding the Missions." Holograph and typed lecture notes.
  - 2. "In a Mission Garden." Printed poem by Clarence Urmy.
  - 3. Clipping on Mission Lecture series.
  - 4. "The Decline of the Missions." Typed lecture notes.
  - 5. Miscellaneous holograph notes.
  - 6. Notes - holograph, partially bound notebook.
  - 7. Life of Father Junipero Serra. Holograph notes from work by Fr. Francis Palou.
- Cherington, Reed B. - California Missions (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. List, holograph of names and subjects regarding missions.
  - 2. "Mission Life." Bound lecture notes, typed.
  - 3. Lecture notes - holograph on cards.
  - 4. Play program for Mission Play.
  - 5. "Mission of the Holy Cross." Printed poem.
  - 6. Map of Monterey County, showing ranches, etc.
- Corbett, Failing and Company (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - 1. A. L. S. from Randmann, Nielson and Co., 1873 October 24
  - 2. A. L. S. from John Skinner, 1875 May 14.
- Doyle, John T. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. Typescript biography (a reminiscence) of George Gordon, signed.
  - 1a. E. W. F. Sloan to George Gordon. A. L. S. 1865 October 16 re: San Francisquito and Rinconada claims, etc.
  - 1b. George Gordon to E. W. Sloan. Letter press 1865 October 16 and statement re: land dispute with Seal.
  - 2. Bound volume. The Pious Fund Case. Printed material and manuscript notes.
  - 3. Legal document re: The Pious Fund Case.
- Evans, Joseph J. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1. Printed invitation to reception for Pres. and Mrs. Harrison, 1891 April 27.
  - 2. Carles N. Felton. T. L. S. to Joseph J. Evans, 1892 February 27.
  - 3. John T. Cutting. T. L (signature stamp) to Joseph J. Evans, 1892 April 13. (With misc. printed invitations, speeches, circulars and announcements).
  - 4. D. M. Burns, secretary Republican State Central Committee. A. L. S., 1894 July 26. (With clips on Evans and other San Franciscans, Calif. Republican Party, business affairs, social, etc. San Franciso and Los Gatos).
  - 5. Morton C. Allen. A. N. S. to Joseph J. Evans, 1892 March 13. N. D. to Roks.
  - 6. W. H. Chamberlain. Tel. to Joseph J. Evans, 1892 May 7. (Expense account, W. J. Kennedy (Bear Club), A. N. S. 1892 April 13. Clips re: Grand Jury duty 1893).
- Felton, Charles N. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook
    This volume contains obituaries and newsclippings pertaining to relations with Hawaiian trade, sugar industry problems, Chinese question and anti-Chinese legislation, activities in Congress, A. N. "M" to [Felton B. Elkins], silver question, wine legislation, tariffs and free trade, plant blights, and public lands, ca. 1886-1914.
- Jones, Louise Coffin (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1. Political cartoons
- Leland, Joseph W. and G. W. Leland (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1. J. W. Leland to "sister" from Brownsville, Texas, 1849 February 12, A. L. S.
  - 2. G. W. Leland to "Sister Eliza" from San Leandro, CA, 1856 October 2, A. L. S.
- Martindale, Dr. John Howard (Map-case Map case, Folder 8a)
  - 1. Photographs, certificates, and other items pertaining to Martindale and his family, 1858-1923.
- McCormick, Rodney - John York (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "A Short Short History of Grandfather York: Boyhood Recollection"
    This history covers 1845 to 1870s and discusses his overland trip in 1845, Napa Valley, the gold rush, Bear Flag Rebellion, John York, David Hudson, Indians, Lake County, St. Helena, Chinese, and the railroad. Xerox of typescript belonging to James H. Snell.
- Oregon History (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Handwritten, bound ms. by Samuel J. Parker, 1893.
    This volume, entitled "The History of Oregon [Territory] in its connection with missions. Especially that of the American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions," pertains to the author's father Samuel Parker, founder of the American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions, between the years of 1832 and 1847. It includes copies of Parker's papers and letters and some copies of Whitman documents; originals noted as being in the archives of the American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions.
- Pease, Vera Jane (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1. Chas. [Smolowski] to Philipp H. Wheeler re watch patents, 1882 October 24, A. N. S.
  - 2. M. H. Hawks, sec. Chicao Open Board of Trade, introducing Phillip H. Wheeler, 1889, January 22, A. L. S.
  - 3. Otay Watch Company and Philip H. Wheeler, employment contract signed by R. D. Perry, Jas. H. Guion, P. H. Wheeler, and J. W. McCool, 1889, February 25, D. S.
  - 4. M. D. Hamilton, letter of recommendation of Wheeler, 1890 November 15, A. L. S.
  - 5. E. H. Miller, letter of recommendation of Wheeler, 1890 November 17, A. L. S.
  - 6. Incorporation of placer mining claims, H. P. McGuire, P. H. Wheeler, A. T. Large, and W. N. Wilbur, 1901 October 10 and 22, T. D. S. and A. D. S.
  - 7. Royal Arch Masons - release of Wheeler from membership in Ohio, 1903 November 9, D. S. (duplicate of 1897 original).
  - 8. R. L. Wilbur to E. E. Robinson re transmittal of above items, 1944 July 6, T. L. S.
  - 9. Letitia Black to [Mrs. Pease?] re pioneering in Colorado in 1946, 1946 December 18, A. L. S.
  - 10. Clipping on Nevada and California ghost towns, Alpha, Omega and Old Dobbins, n. d.
- San Francisco Browning Society (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1. Helen MacKnight Doyle to Mrs. Sloss, 1952 January 28, T. L. S.
  - 2. Minutes of meeting, by Mabel M. [Elzas], 1953 October 2, A. D. S.
- San Francisco Reform Movement (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1. & 2. Programs with menu for luncheon meeting of The Citizens' League of Justice, 1909 April 29.
  - 3. The Liberator Vol. II, No. 9, 1910 February 5.
  - 4. Printed circular letter and list of names, S. F. Women's Civic Club, 1910 June 28.
  - 5. Printed invitation, banquet in honor of Francis J. Heney, 1910 November 15.
- Stevenson, E. A. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1. A. L. S. to Horsley and Nash, 1857 September 17.
- Townsend Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 15)
  This volume consists of typescript copies of documents relating almost exclusively to the estates of Dr. John Townsend and his wife Elizabeth. The originals were loaned by Moses Schallenberger and copied by Katherine A. Chandler in 1898 as part of a history thesis. It covers the years 1846 to 1858 and includes a table of contents.
- Miscelleanous Items (Map-case Map case, Folder 16)
  - 1. Diagram of a 15" disel electric pipe line dredge, 1923 April.
  - 2. Society of California Pioneers Membership of Abram W. Stratton who arrived in California 1849 October 12, dated 1873 April 23
  - 3. Committee of Vigilance of San Francisco Membership of A. W. Stratton.
  - 4. San Francisco Fire Department Membership of A. W. Stratton, 1855 March 5.
- Cherington, Reed B. Notecards on California missions. (Box 3)
- Cherington, Reed B. Notecards on T. O. Larkin Part I. (Box 4)
- Cherington, Reed B. Notecards on T. O. Larkin Part II. (Box 5)
- Finney, S. J. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - 1. Scrapbook of newspaper clippings on the California legislature, 1870 February 17 to 1870 April 12.
  - 2. Scrapbook of newspaper clippings on the California legislature and drafts of some bills, 1872.
- Savage Mining Company (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - 1. Thirteen deeds, 1864-1891.
  - 2. Three court documents, 1867, 1869 and 1887.
- Parker Maps (Map-case Map case, Folder 19)
  - 1. Western United States Whitman Trail 1834-1847.
  - 2. Oregon Territory 1838